<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright © 2022-2024 Nikolaos Dionysopoulos

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free
Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included
in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
-->
<book version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Joomla Extensions Development</title>

    <subtitle>The missing <trademark>Joomla</trademark> reference for
    extension developers</subtitle>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>

      <personblurb>
        <para>Nicholas is a software developer, mostly known for his work in
        Akeeba Backup and Admin Tools. He's been writing Joomla extensions
        since 2006 — and software in general for another decade, since his
        middle school years. He is a regular contributor to the Joomla
        project. When he's not writing code he enjoys writing documentation to
        spread the knowledge and the Joomla love. He lives in Greece with his
        wife, daughter and their two cats.</para>
      </personblurb>
    </author>

    <pubdate>January 2024</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2022-2024</year>

      <holder>Nikolaos Dionysopoulos</holder>
    </copyright>

    <abstract>
      <para>Developing Joomla extensions is fun and fulfilling. However, its
      API evolves to better suit the changing times and PHP best practices.
      When Joomla 4 came out with its richer, brand new API there was no
      documentation to tell developers how to update and keep developing their
      extensions. Moreover, over a decade of API stagnation and lack of
      documentation led developers to complacency, bad code, and
      unmaintainable code. This book aims to distill my experience writing
      Joomla software since 2006 and includes some useful background on how
      some features were decided, how they are meant to be used, and where
      they fit in the larger picture of writing efficient, maintainable code.
      This is neither a tutorial nor a reference book. It's more of a
      practical guide through the Joomla extensions development API.</para>

      <para>This book covers development of Joomla! extensions under Joomla
      versions 4 and 5.</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the section entitled "<link
      linkend="fdl-license">GNU Free Documentation License</link>".</para>

      <para>—</para>

      <para>This work is not affiliated with or endorsed by the Joomla!
      Project. It is not supported or warranted by the Joomla! Project or Open
      Source Matters. The Joomla! logo is used under a limited license granted
      by Open Source Matters, the trademark holder in the United States and
      other countries.</para>

      <para>—</para>

      <para>All code found in the code samples in this book is free software;
      you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU
      General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation;
      either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later
      version.</para>

      <para>This sample program code is distributed in the hope that it will
      be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty
      of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the <link
      linkend="gpl">GNU General Public License</link> for more details.</para>

      <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
      along with this sample program code; if not, write to the Free Software
      Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301
      USA</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <xi:include href="sections/preface.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/concepts.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/components.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/plugins.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/modules.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/advice.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/fdl.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sections/gpl.xml"/>
</book>
