<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright © 2022 Nikolaos Dionysopoulos

Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free
Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included
in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
-->
<preface
        version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
        xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
        xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
        xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
        xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xml:id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section xml:id="intro-about">
        <title>About this book</title>

        <para>I started writing this book in August 2022 as a quick reference
            for myself and other third party developers writing Joomla 4 extensions,
            or migrating our extensions to Joomla 4's native MVC.</para>

        <para>While Joomla 4 has an amazing, rich and powerful architecture and
            API it does not have any real developer-facing documentation. The
            documentation you will find is outdated, chaotic and leaves you running
            for your life.</para>

        <para>I am making every effort to make this book approachable to all
            levels of developers, from the novice who's barely hacked together their
            first plugin to the seasoned expert with dozens of extensions under
            their belt. However, to keep things relatively simple and because I am
            doing this unpaid, on my limited free time, I decided to take a few
            shortcuts here and there. I do not explain every concept in great
            detail, I try to explain it in practical detail.</para>

        <para>If you want to see what a real world Joomla extension looks like I
            urge you to take a look at and dissect the Joomla 4 extensions my
            company, Akeeba Ltd, has published free of charge. The simplest
            component to start with is Akeeba ContactUs. The most complete
            combination of a component, plugins and several modules we have
            published is Akeeba Ticket System — even the free of charge version uses
            most of the features I am describing in this book.</para>

        <para>Hopefully, you will find my approach pragmatic and result-driven
            instead of a dry, technical document. If you have suggestions for
            improvement or would like to sponsor this work feel free to contact me
            through the Contact Me page on <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.dionysopoulos.me">dionysopoulos.me</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="about-me">
        <title>About the author</title>

        <para><mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="https://www.gravatar.com/avatar/d8bb182ef0e061a3c4959a2d659e4252.jpg?s=256"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>Hi, I am Nicholas. I am a Mechanical Engineer turned
            Software Engineer. I am from and still live in Greece with my wife,
            daughter and our two naughty cats.</para>

        <para>I've been into computers since I was 11 years olds, at the dawn of
            the 1990s. Back then dinosaurs were still walking among us, haircuts
            were <emphasis>weird</emphasis>, personal computers were the size of a
            small backpack and had <emphasis>far less</emphasis> computing power
            than your average smart lightbulb. Only one of the previous statements
            is false. I immediately took to programming for, as I said to my parents
            at the time, “I want to learn how to make this machine do things for me
            so I don't have to do them”. LIttle did I know what I was getting myself
            into…</para>

        <para>I've been using Joomla as a site integrator and extensions
            developer since it was called Mambo, back in 2004. I wrote my first
            mass-distributed extension called JoomlaPack in October 2006 while
            taking a two week break from my day job at the time as a business
            consultant. One thing led to another, JoomlaPack became Akeeba Backup
            and I gave up on business consultancy and mechanical engineering to
            become a full time software engineer.</para>

        <para>I've been actively participating in the Joomla community since
            2009. I am a regular Joomla contributor and not just writing code. I've
            been involved in community outreach efforts and instigated the events
            leading to the beginning of the Joomla 4 effort. I still contribute to
            Joomla and, if I want to be honest with myself, I will continue doing
            that until Joomla or myself is no more, whichever comes first.</para>

        <para>I am neurodivergent (ADHD) and have a particular sense of humour.
            I firmly believe that life's too short to take it seriously. You'll see
            that a lot in this book. I don't care about writing a dry, boring book,
            especially on a subject as dry and boring as writing software.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="intro-j4-features">
        <title>New Joomla 4 features at a glance</title>

        <para>Joomla 4 is a smorgasbord of new features, improvements and much
            needed changes. Unfortunately, a year into its release you'd be hard
            pressed to find any kind of documentation of what these are and how they
            can impact your software development practices. I will try to give you
            the 30,000-feet overview of what <emphasis>I</emphasis> found to be the
            most important changes.</para>

        <para><link linkend="concepts-namespaces"><emphasis
                role="bold">Namespaces</emphasis></link>. As you may remember, ever
            since Joomla 3.3 the legacy class names (e.g. <code>JUri</code>) changed
            to a namespaced equivalent (e.g. <code>Joomla\CMS\Uri\Uri</code>). In
            Joomla 4 a lot of the legacy classes stopped working. You can find out
            these changes neatly codified along with tools to mass convert your
            extensions in my <link
                    xlink:href="http://github.com/nikosdion/joomlatypehints">Joomla Type
                Hints</link> repository. In Joomla 4 the namespacing work went even
            deeper, having all classes in components, modules, plugins and templates
            also support namespaces — if you use the new, Joomla 4 API for
            developing extensions. This is a game-changer concept! Namespaced
            classes follow the <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.php-fig.org/psr/psr-4/">PSR-4</link>
            specification. Joomla caches and registers the PSR-4 mappings between
            namespace prefixes and directories on your site which means that
            <emphasis>you can safely use any class of any extension anywhere without
                having to use <code>include</code> or <code>require</code> ever
                again</emphasis>. This greatly reduces the possibility for bugs and
            massively improves the performance of Joomla and its extensions.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold"><link
                linkend="concepts-container">Dependency Injection Container / Service
            Locator</link></emphasis>. Joomla 1.x to 3.x inclusive had this annoying
            <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/God_object">God
                Object</link> called the Joomla Factory (<code>JFactory</code> or
            <code>\Joomla\CMS\Factory</code>). It had a very opinionated approach on
            instantiating all sorts of globally used services, from the application
            itself, to the database, to the user objects, to the mailer object. If
            you wanted to write Unit Tests for your extension — or Joomla itself —
            it was the bane of your existence. In Joomla 4 we instead have a
            Container. It is not a real <link
                    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_injection">Dependency
                Injection Container</link> as much as it is a <link
                    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Service_locator_pattern">Service
                Locator</link>, meaning that it won't magically instantiate an object
            based on the type definitions in its class' constructor but it will let
            you retrieve the services you need to inject to your objects. Each
            extension — component, module, plugin and template — gets its own
            service locator and its own extension object which uses it. This makes
            it far easier to write unit tests for your code, especially your Models
            (which is where most of your business logic, therefore your code that
            needs testing, should already be).</para>

        <para><link linkend="concepts-webassetmanager"><emphasis role="bold">Web
            Asset Manager</emphasis></link>. In the past, whenever we wanted to load
            a JavaScript or CSS file we'd have to load its dependencies and finally
            our file. For example we might want to load jQuery, then load some
            Bootstrap core JavaScript files, then our JavaScript file. Each
            extension would do that and it lead to several chicken and egg problems.
            What if file A from extension X depends on files B and C and file B from
            extension Y depends on files C and D but D must be loaded before C?
            Bummer. The Web Asset Manager codifies the dependencies in a way which
            lets Joomla resolve them. It also lets you define alternative
            dependencies,e.g. a different JavaScript file to load depending on
            whether the user's browser supports <link
                    xlink:href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Guide/Modules">JavaScript
                modules</link> or not, and asset groups, e.g. a collection of CSS and
            JavaScript which are meant to be loaded together. This lets you split
            your CSS and JavaScript into smaller files which load in the correct
            order and improve the performance of your user's site.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="com-j3-vs-j4-mvc">A new
            MVC</link></emphasis>. The MVC in Joomla 1.5 to 3.10 inclusive had
            changed very little. Previous attempts to modernise it failed
            ignominiously because they simultaneously failed to go far enough and
            maintain <acronym>b/c</acronym> (backwards compatibility). Joomla 4 has
            a new MVC model which is based on Dependency Injection and namespaces,
            it is more prescriptive, more flexible and more powerful than its
            predecessors. You can very easily extend a frontend model from a backend
            model instead of writing the same code twice or doing a contortionist
            act with PHP Traits. You can easily create custom HTML helpers without
            calling static functions, use categories without writing precarious
            database code, create object-oriented URL routers and much more which we
            will explore in this book.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hide-able inline help</emphasis>. Remember
            how Joomla 3 XML Forms looked like a word vomit with all the inline help
            text (field descriptions) being always visible? This was a bad interface
            for experienced users. At the same time, Joomla 4.0 removing all inline
            help text made the interface inapproachable for newcomers and end
            clients meant to use the site. With Joomla 4.1 it is now possible to
            have hide-able inline help text in your forms and your component
            configuration. The field descriptions are hidden by default and the user
            can show them by clicking on the <guibutton>Show Inline Help</guibutton>
            button in the interface. Now your extensions' interface can be
            simultaneously approachable for both new and experienced users.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Prepared statements</emphasis>. SQL
            injection vulnerabilities have been almost <emphasis>de
                rigueur</emphasis> for any web software, Joomla extensions being no
            exception to that. Sure, Joomla does have some very nifty tools to get
            filtered input and escape it when placed inside database queries but not
            all input can be escaped sufficiently if you do not know its
            <emphasis>type</emphasis> (integer, string, array of one or the other).
            Moreover, despite best intentions, accidents can and do happen, e.g.
            forgetting to escape one piece of input you assumed it's an integer but
            it came through a path which never did check the input type nor did it
            try to typecast it to an integer! Joomla 4 introduced <link
                    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prepared_statement">prepared
                statements</link> which make these oversights and corner cases a thing
            of the past. You tell the query builder where you expect potentially
            user-originating data in your query, which data to use in there and what
            type this data is. You are guaranteed safe execution without worrying
            about SQL injection <emphasis>unless you try really hard</emphasis> to
            NOT let Joomla use a prepared statement. On the flip side, there are a
            few types of SQL queries which cannot execute in the context of prepared
            statements and required some code contortion to execute.</para>

        <para><link linkend="com-mailtemplates"><emphasis role="bold">Mail
            templates</emphasis></link>. In the past there were two ways to handle
            email for your extension. You could send plain text only email using
            language strings OR you would have to invent your own email template
            management. The former led to ugly email messages. The latter required
            reinventing a very complex device on each and every of your components.
            If you did not have a component, tough luck. Darn! Joomla 4's mail
            templates feature allows your users to use the Joomla WYSIWYG editor to
            create rich email templates with placeholders to be replaced by data
            provided by your extension. This feature looks half-finished in Joomla 4
            as it has no obvious way to register or update email templates. Don't
            worry, though, we do have a way to work around its shortcomings,
            complete with example code.</para>

        <para><link linkend="com-scheduled-tasks"><emphasis
                role="bold">Scheduled Tasks</emphasis></link>. Many extensions need to
            periodically execute some kind of code. For example, sending email
            newsletters, updating the prices of thousands of SKUs in an online shop
            from an Excel or XML file, running backups, you name it! In the past we
            had to reinvent the wheel on each extension we built. For example, we
            created ‘special’ URLs in our components or through com_ajax to be
            accessed with wget, cURL or a service like WebCRON.org periodically; or
            we created CLI scripts to be used with CRON jobs. We almost always
            offered more than one way to do things which led to a certain degree of
            code duplication. In all cases, the user was responsible for setting up
            CRON jobs or the equivalent on a third party service for every single
            task they needed to be executed periodically. This was a tall ask!
            Joomla 4.1 and later offers a new Scheduled Tasks feature which allows
            users to select which tasks they want to be executed, when to execute
            them and even configure their execution parameters — all within the
            familiar Joomla user interface. It even lets the task scheduler to be
            executed three ways: with a command line CRON job, a URL-based CRON job
            or automatically based on visitor traffic (lazy scheduling). The end
            user has to set up just the one CRON job or, if they are using lazy
            scheduling, just flip a switch.</para>

        <para><link linkend="com-cli"><emphasis role="bold">CLI
            Application</emphasis></link>. In the past we had to create bespoke CLI
            scripts for every task each of our extensions needed to allow to be
            executed from a command line context, be it a CRON job or a manually
            executed CLI helper tool. This required creating a new application and
            contend with the two facts that a) the base class changed at least twice
            in the last ten years and b) it lacked a lot of methods several core and
            third party classes were expecting to be present. This led to a lot of
            reinventing the wheel. The Joomla CLI Application is like a built-in
            version of WordPress' WP-CLI or Drupal's Drush in that it's based on the
            Symfony Console Components and can be easily extended using plugins
            which register command classes. Used wisely, it can enhance your
            extensions and help your advanced users who can use the CLI to automate
            things around their site.</para>

        <para><link linkend="com-api"><emphasis role="bold">API
            Application</emphasis></link>. Joomla has historically been an HTML-only
            application. Yes, sure, you can have JSON, XML, Feed and Raw views but
            they feel bolted onto the HTML application; they are not a real API to
            your component. Joomla 4 introduced a brand-new application, the
            ApiApplication which lives in the <filename>api</filename> directory of
            your site. For now it's only accessible to Super Users but it provides a
            real RESTful JSON-based API to components which integrate with it.
            Integrating your component with the API application is as easy as
            creating a Web Services plugin and adding a few easy to create
            controllers and views in the API part of your component. That is to say,
            your component now has a backend, a frontend and an API side. You don't
            <emphasis>have</emphasis> to integrate with the API application but if
            you have something which could benefit from automation it is strongly
            encouraged to do so.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Dashboards</emphasis>. Between Joomla 1.0
            and 3.10 inclusive Joomla only ever offered one dashboard, the main
            Control Panel page which loaded when you logged into your site's
            backend. In Joomla 1.0 to 1.6 it was hard-coded and inflexible. I added
            the ability to use plugins to render custom action buttons in Joomla
            1.7, based on my experience with my software. Starting with Joomla 3.0
            you could now publish <emphasis>modules</emphasis> to add information
            panes to the Control Panel dashboard. If you wanted the same experience
            in your extension… tough luck. You would have to reinvent the wheel.
            Joomla 4.0 and later allow you to set up <emphasis>one or more dashboard
                pages for your own component</emphasis> which appear in the Joomla menu
            structure, under your component's menu item, and where you and your end
            users can publish any number of modules.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Layouts everywhere</emphasis>. A lot of the
            HTML generated by Joomla, even throughout version 3, was statically
            coded in the PHP files implementing the business logic, making any kind
            of customisation impossible (or, at the very least, requiring a very
            judicious application of in-memory code editing, buffer stream wrappers
            and Reflection). Let's just say that if you disagreed with how a certain
            form field or HTML helper rendered its HTML you were out of luck.
            Layouts were introduced in Joomla 3.4 and later versions did make better
            use of them in various places but you still had to contend with several
            of the same issues. Not anymore! Joomla 4 uses layouts for every kind of
            HTML output. If you want to override how some core code renders in your
            component or your template you can easily do that by overriding the
            layout. Likewise, you are encouraged to use Layouts everywhere you have
            reusable HTML output in your extensions to make it easier for end users
            to override them in their template.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Media options per component</emphasis>.
            Joomla 3.4 introduced an upload checker for all uploaded files based on
            the work I had done in Admin Tools. This was a massive leap in security
            as we codified the basic upload checks and encapsulated them in a way
            that made them run automatically whenever you were handling uploads.
            However, this was controlled by the Media component's
            (<code>com_media</code>) settings. This was great if your extension only
            ever needed static media files to be uploaded. If you wanted to allow
            your users to upload non-media files, or files otherwise not acceptable
            anywhere else <code>com_media</code> was exposed, such as ZIP, 7Z, and
            RAR files in a helpdesk component, you had to modify the Media options,
            allowing these files <emphasis>everywhere</emphasis>. The unfortunate
            solution to that was that third party component developers chose to
            <emphasis>disable</emphasis> the upload checks, undoing the security
            improvements we added in Joomla 3.4. This is no longer the case! Joomla
            4 allows each component to have its own, private copy of Media settings
            for its own uploads. Any upload being handled by your component (not
            <code>com_media</code>!) will have these private settings applied. It's
            a bit of a chore BUT it lets you provide a much safer option for
            uploading files through your extension.</para>

        <para>There are many more improvements which I will not cover in this
            book. If you found out something cool and you'd like me to write a
            section for it, please do let me know. I can't promise it will
            definitely make it into the book but I will at least promise to give it
            a good thought and most likely a good try.</para>
    </section>
</preface>
